<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the honourable the knights, citizens and burgesses, in Parliament assembled; the deplorable case and humble petition of Dr. Titus Oates.</title>
            <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O56A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826616</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1766:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the honourable the knights, citizens and burgesses, in Parliament assembled; the deplorable case and humble petition of Dr. Titus Oates.</title>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the St. John's College (University of Cambridge) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1689-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:31019:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>To the Honourable The Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, in PARLIAMENT Aſſembled; The Deplorable Caſe and Humble Petition of Dr. <hi>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OATES.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
            <p>THAT your Petitioner in the Year 1678, diſcovered a horrid Popiſh Conſpiracy, for the Deſtruction of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and his preſent Majeſty, and the Proteſtant Religion within theſe Kingdoms; and proved it ſo fully, that ſeveral Parliaments and Courts of Juſtice, before whom he gave his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, declared their belief of it by publick Votes and the Condemnation of ſeveral of the Conſpirators. THAT upon this Account the Popiſh Party purſued your Petitioner with an implacable Malice, attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral times to take away his Life; and being defeated in that Attempt, they firſt procured the ſaid King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second to withdraw that Protection and Subſiſtance that the ſaid King had allowed him at the Requeſt of ſeveral Parliaments, which was 40 <hi>l. per</hi> Month; and then inſtigated his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to proſecute your Petitioner in an Action of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> for ſpeaking this Notorious Truth, (<hi>viz.</hi>) That he the ſaid D. of <hi>York</hi> was <hi>Reconciled to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and that it is High-Treaſon to be ſo Reconciled;</hi> wherein a Verdict and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for 100000 <hi>l.</hi> Damages were obtained againſt your Petitioner, and your Petitioner committed to the <hi>King's Bench</hi> Priſon.</p>
            <p>AFTER this the Popiſh Party obtained leave from King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> to prefer two ſeveral Indictments againſt your Petitioner for two pretended Perjuries, in his Evidence concerning the ſaid Conſpiracy; which they brought on to a Trial in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Second: and your Petitioner upon the Teſtimony of theſe very Witneſſes who had Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted him in three former Trials, and were disbelieved, (through the partial Behaviour of the Chief Juſtice <hi>Jefferies,</hi> in brow-beating your Petitioner's Witneſſes and miſleading the Juries) was Convicted of the ſaid pretended Perjuries, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this Inhumane and unparallel'd Sentence, <hi>viz. To pay</hi> 2000 <hi>Marks to the King, to be diveſted of his Canonical Habit; to be brought into</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall <hi>with a Paper upon his Head, with this Inſcription,</hi> Titus Oates Convicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on full Evidence of two horrid Perjuries; <hi>to ſtand in and upon the Pillory two ſeveral Days for the ſpace of an hour; to be Whipt by the Common-Hangman from</hi> Aldgate <hi>to Newgate on</hi> Wedneſday, <hi>and</hi> Friday <hi>following from</hi> Newgate <hi>to</hi> Tyburn; <hi>to ſtand in and upon the Pillory five times every Year of his Life, and to remain a Priſoner during Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS Sentence (as your Petitioner believes) was to murder him, and was executed accordingly with all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Barbarity, he having ſuffered ſome thouſands of Stripes, whereby he was put to unſpakeable Tortures, and lay ten Weeks under the Chirurgions Hands: neither did their Malice and Cruelty ceaſe here, but becauſe your Petitioner (through the Mercy of God ſupporting him, and the extraordinary Skill of a Judicious Chirurgion) outlived that barbarous Uſage, ſome of them got into his Chamber whileſt he was weak in his Bed, and attempted to pull of the Plaiſters applied to cure his Back, and threatned to deſtroy him.</p>
            <p>THAT nothing within their Power and Malice might be wanting to compleat your Petitioner's Miſery, they procured him to be loaded with Irons of exceſſive Weight for one whole Year without any Intermiſſion, even when his Legs were ſwollen with the Gout, and to be ſhut up in the Hole or Dungeon of the ſaid Priſon, whereby he became impaired of his Limbs, and contracted Convulſion-Fits to the Hazard of his Life. All which Illegal Proceedings and Barbarous Inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, were not only intended againſt your Petitioner as a Revenge upon him, but likewiſe to caſt a Reproach upon the Wiſdom and Honour of four ſucceſſive Parliaments, who had given him Credit, and upon the publick Juſtice of the Nation.</p>
            <p>DURING the Time that this Proſecution was upon your Petitioner, ſeveral Noblemen and Gentlemen, Citizens and others contributed 4000 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> for his Support and Maintenance, which your Petitioner enjoyed till his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty King, <hi>William,</hi> at the requeſt of both Houſes of Parliament, reſtored to him your Petitioner, the foreſaid Penſion of 40 <hi>l. per Menſom,</hi> after having been deprived thereof nine Years, to his loſs above 5000 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THAT your Petitioner enjoyed the ſaid Allowance of 40 <hi>l. per</hi> Month, from <hi>September</hi> 1689. till <hi>Lady-day</hi> in the Year 1692. after which time your Petitioner had not his Penſion paid him, to the undoing of your poor Petitioner, his Friends withdrawing their Bounty from him, when his Majeſty reſtored your Petitioner to his ſaid Penſion, they judging him to be provided for during his Life: ſo that your Petitioner is ruined, he having in the time of his Sufferings, and ſince his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of 40 <hi>l. per</hi> Month was taken away, contracted Debts, for which he hath bin ſued by his Creditors, and hath bin Arreſted and his, Goods taken in Execution; and muſt have periſhed had not the <hi>Lords of the Treaſury</hi> relieved your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner with the Sum of 350 <hi>l.</hi> with which Sum your poor Petitioner did pay his Creditors in part, but will be ſued for the Remainder of his Debts which amounts to 500 <hi>l.</hi> and his poor Wife and Family muſt periſh, and your Petitioner ſtarve at laſt in a Priſon, unleſs this Honourable Houſe do take your poor Petitioner's deplorable Caſe into their tender Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his ſaid Penſion of 40 <hi>l. per</hi> Month being his whole and only Subſiſtance, he having no Eſtate to live upon.</p>
            <p>THE Premiſes conſidered, your Petitioner throws himſelf at the Feet of this Honourable Houſe, and pray your Honours to take his deplorable Caſe into your tender Conſideration; ſo that your Petitioner may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Arrears of his Penſion to diſcharge his Debts, and that he may be reſtor'd to his Penſion of 40 <hi>l. per</hi> Month, that he and his diſtreſſed Family may not ſtarve for Want of Bread.</p>
            <p>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
